Beth: The way Autism is portrayed and
reported in the media is incredibly
powerful in educating and influencing the
public both positively and negatively.
This can be via TV or tabloid
news, films and TV series
and also across social media.
There are also obvious and clear
difference between how individuals
on the spectrum were portrayed
in the past compared to today.
Joe: While the majority of filmmakers,
TV producers, journalists and so forth,
do not create pieces about people with
autism to purposefully misrepresent
or disparage them, it still happens.
There are many misconceptions associated
with Autism spectrum disorder and these
can be fueled by misrepresentation.
These may appear at first hand,
to be positive portrayals, however
this can create a belief that all
individuals with Autism are the same.
Beth: More modern films and television
shows, portray those with autism as very
high functioning geniuses with quirky
personalities, or ‘mute’ or ‘savant’, but
they omit certain groups and don’t portray
the range of characteristics that are on
the spectrum perpetuating the stereotype.
Some people therefore see individuals
with Autism as high functioning with
atypical abilities, such as enhanced
ability for doing things, such as working
with numbers, memory, music, drawing etc.
However, others just see the
behavioural issues and lack of empathy
that are only some of the extreme
elements involved in the spectrum.
Joe: So we can see that Individuals
with Autism spectrum disorder face many
different challenges of stigmatisation
and stereotyping due to the public
perception more often than not created
by their portrayal in the media.
If the media continues to portray
Autism in a more positive way
especially reflecting the nuanced
characteristics of individuals on
the spectrum, society should become
more informed and tolerant and try to
understand the nature of the individual.
That would then in turn mean they
are more likely to understand
and appreciate the differences.
Beth: Many high profile creative and
pioneering individuals of the past showed
signs of being on the autism spectrum to
some degree but this cannot be verified.
However, a current prominent figure
and environmental activist in the
world today, who can be verified, is
Swedish teen activist, Greta Thunberg,
and she is now quite open about her
autism spectrum disorder diagnosis.
Joe: Greta started protesting at the age
of 15, about climate crisis, and developed
an unprecedented global movement in 2018.
She is known worldwide as the public
face of the ‘school climate strike
movement’ and has spoken about her
Asperger’s syndrome diagnosis, after
she was criticised over the condition.
Beth: She said on Twitter, that before
she started her climate action campaign;
“I had no energy, no friends
and I didn’t speak to anyone.
I just sat alone at home,
with an eating disorder.”
Joe: She also wasn’t open about her
diagnosis in the beginning, as she
knew people would see it as a negative.
However, Greta doesn’t view herself as
having a disability, but instead she
has a different way of seeing something.
Beth: While acknowledging that her
diagnosis has limited her in the past,
Greta has tweeted “I have Asperger’s
and that means I’m sometimes a bit
different from the norm,” and she sees
being different as having a “superpower”.
Joe: For many Greta Thunberg’s diagnosis
of Asperger’s Syndrome, has not
lowered their opinion of her, and the
qualities and characteristics that she
exudes, simply make her who she is.
Today she continues to inspire people
around the world, young and old, with
or without autism, to step outside their
comfort zone and make a difference.
Beth: Can you think of any other famous
examples of people who are public about
being on the spectrum, perhaps they are
someone who may have been misunderstood
or misinterpreted in the past, or perhaps
they have always been understood and
appreciated for what makes them, them.
Try researching into other public
figures and their experiences with
Autism Spectrum Disorder and see what
you find, you never know, some examples
may reflect someone in a new light.